### **Usman Akram** | (281) 235-8566 | <u>usman.akram96@gmail.com</u>

#### **OBJECTIVE**

Highly analytical and process-oriented engineering student with in-depth knowledge of database types, research methodologies, big data capture, curation, manipulation, and visualization. To furnish insights, analytics and business intelligence used to advance opportunity identification, process reengineering and corporate growth.

### WEBSITE

usmanakram96.github.io

## **EDUCATION**

College of Engineering, University of Texas at Tyler

Bachelors in Mechanical Engineering

Overall GPA: 3.27

Expected: Spring 2023

University of Houston, Main Campus

Minor in Mathematics Rewarded: Spring 2018

San Jacinto College, South Campus

Associates of Applied Science and Mathematics Rewarded: Spring 2016

## **EXPERIENCE**

### Natural Language Processing Data Analyst, WeLocalize, TX

Feb 2019 – Present

- Analyze data for localization services, adhering to quality standards.
- Employed knowledge of localized culture and language traits for analytic purposes.
- Write and report relevant bugs and errors through the client internal issue tracking database.

# Technical Data Advisory Consultant, Brinks Home Security, TX

August 2018 - Feb 2019

- Create and customize a system designed to maximize security for residential areas.
- Serve the interest of my client to design and protect their home.
- Ability to work as part of a team but also independently and on own initiative.
- Crisis management when required.

## Data Analytics Manager, Brookstone, Friendswood, TX

**July 2015 – June 2018** 

- Analyze and provide quality reports on day-to-day data operations within the store.
- Follow instructions from engineers of the company for layout of products.
- Problem solving any design and faulty mechanics.

## **PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS**

- Entry-level data analytics professional; recently completed the Google Data Analytics Professional certificate.
- Optimizing and presenting efficient improvements for a Vehicle HVAC system.
- Programming designing and developing a simulation for a working Heat Exchanger.
- Successfully interpolating vast amounts of machine data and creating engineering grade lab reports.
- Drawing Mechanical linkage systems capable of carrying out cycled tasks with proper degrees of motion.

### **SKILLS**

Solidworks	Google Analytics	Data Structure	Quantitative Methods
AutoCAD	SQL	R	Regression Analysis
Programming	Tableau	Mathcad	Experimental Design & Analysis
Microsoft Office	MATLAB	Big Query	Statistical Computing Methods
Data Technologies	Simulink	Data Visualization	Research Data Management